<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The dovvnfall of the pretended divine authoritie of the hierarchy into the Sea of Rome. From some arguments, and motives, to the finall extirpation of that unlawfull government of the prelacy: as having no foundation in the Scriptures, but onely in that filthy dung-hill of the canon law of the Popes authoritie, and therefore antichristian. And so they are wrongfully blamed for abuse of their offices, the very nature and right use whereof is to overthrow churches and kingdoms, laws of God &amp; man, to propagate the kingdom of Antichrist: the office is so bad as cannot be used otherwise. Also their dangerous practises discovered: and the great objection of martyr-prelates answered. by V.N.V.</title>
            <author>Fenwicke, John, d. 1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85214</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859452</idno>
  <idno type="VID">111535</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240860280</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F720A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E160_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1331</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859452</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99859452e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85214)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111535)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 28:E160[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The dovvnfall of the pretended divine authoritie of the hierarchy into the Sea of Rome. From some arguments, and motives, to the finall extirpation of that unlawfull government of the prelacy: as having no foundation in the Scriptures, but onely in that filthy dung-hill of the canon law of the Popes authoritie, and therefore antichristian. And so they are wrongfully blamed for abuse of their offices, the very nature and right use whereof is to overthrow churches and kingdoms, laws of God &amp; man, to propagate the kingdom of Antichrist: the office is so bad as cannot be used otherwise. Also their dangerous practises discovered: and the great objection of martyr-prelates answered. by V.N.V.</title>
                  <author>Fenwicke, John, d. 1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno [1641]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date from chronogram: ReX ChrIstVs, Vt VerVs, regnVM paæ DestrVet.</note>
                  <note>Anonymously published by John Fenwicke --Cf. Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111535:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:111535:1"/>
            <p>THE DOVVNFALL OF THE PRETENDED Divine Authoritie of the Hierarchy into the Sea of ROME. <hi>FROM</hi> Some Arguments, and Motives, to the finall Extirpation of that unlawfull government of the PRELACY: as having no foundation in the Scriptures, but onely in that filthy dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill of the Canon Law of the Popes Authoritie, and therefore Antichristian. <hi>And</hi> So they are wrongfully blamed for abuse of their offices, the very nature and right use whereof is to overthrow Churches and Kingdoms, Laws of God &amp; man, to propagate the kingdom of Antichrist: the office is so bad as cannot be used otherwise. <hi>Also their dangerous practises discovered: and the great Objection of Martyr-Prelates answered.</hi> By <hi>Ʋ. N. Ʋ.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>I know thy works, and thy labour, and patience, and how thou canst not endure them which are evill, and thou haste tryed them which say they are Apostles and are not, and haste found them lyers. <bibl>Apoc. 2. 2.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Ostentantes se se quasi sint pastores ecclesiae, quasi sint Episcopi cum sint merae umbrae, personae lupercales, statuae mutae, &amp; picturati trunci.</p>
               <p>Sub magnifico Episcoporum titulo, totum Mundum perdentes.</p>
               <bibl>Luther: de falso nom: &amp; ordine Episcoporum. <hi>Tom. 2. Vitebergae. p.</hi> 330.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno ReX ChrIstVs, Vt VerVs, regnVM papae DestrVet.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:111535:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:111535:2"/>
            <head>Ad Chariss: suum, Ʋ. N. Ʋ.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>PAstorum in orbe cernimus</l>
               <l>Ovilis Christi copiam:</l>
               <l>Pauci ah! quibus corde Dei</l>
               <l>Est gloriae meditatio:</l>
               <l>Sed ventris esse plurimos</l>
               <l>Britannae pastores, magis</l>
               <l>Videmus addictos papae</l>
               <l>Traditionibus impijs:</l>
               <l>Cujus superbos spiritus</l>
               <l>Sic, qui induerunt at{que} opes</l>
               <l>Ejus relictas possident</l>
               <l>Quas devorant voraciter:</l>
               <l>Queîs imminent regaliter:</l>
               <l>Et veritatis deprimunt</l>
               <l>Veros patrones, &amp; Dei</l>
               <l>Veri timentes opprimunt</l>
               <l>In gratiam nisi papae</l>
               <l>Sui{que} commodi, &amp; sui</l>
               <l>Honoris eminentiae.</l>
               <l>Sed ipsa quae fluunt Dei</l>
               <l>Ex fonte verbi Limpido</l>
               <l>Hos judicant, hos comprobant,</l>
               <l>Antistites papae imperî,</l>
               <l>Qui templa tot deglutiunt</l>
               <l>Qui templa tot tot devorant.</l>
               <l>Ne quis per illos devius</l>
               <l>Aberret à Dei via</l>
               <l>Fugiat{que} tales impios</l>
               <l>Et fastuosos clericos</l>
               <l>Falsos{que} pastores procul.</l>
               <l>procul.</l>
               <l>procul.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>In gratiam scripsit Inanes Arce viros.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:111535:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>COURTEOUS READER;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF duty to Religion and Subjects liberties; if loyalty to soveraigne Authoritie; if long and heavy pressures un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the enemies of all these may challenge any privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge at this time; then may I crave leave to creepe in amongst the crowd without presumption, in this abysse of troubles, with my present (to this great work in hand for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation) composed of naked truth clad in her owne colours, in a few succinct Arguments, closely backing one another, as lincks in a chaine, drawing all one way in one strong cord, not one of which I conceive could be wanting, though I have stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died as much brevity as might stand with perspicuitie, in a bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinesse so very weighty, as to give vigour and life to the active axiome of the time, and present exigent, for the finall extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the usurped duplicated authoritie of the Prelacy; the great boll or branch of the Romish Hierarchy: Eclipsing all our glory, eluding all Authoritie, by their lofty dignitie and innate Antipathy to all true Church policy, and our Parliamentary sublyme authoritie, and noble designes, to which above all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane service I professe to be devoted, and to which I here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent my homage and hostage of my best endeavours. If herein thou findest any thing worthy of observance, use it to thine ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage for the common good.</p>
            <p>Every one within his limits improving his endeavours and interest in this present honourable Parliament, to make the Hydraes head of Prelacy, with all the corrupt members of that
<pb facs="tcp:111535:3"/> body, the holocaust to expiate the wrath of God so long threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned against this Land defiled with their abhominations, and bloody cruelties, in their long opposition of Christs Kingly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and that by an Antichristian tyrannicall government, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compatible with all Christian policy and free subjects liberties, the vindicating whereof shall assuredly adde more lustre to this ancient Kingdomes glory, and our Parliaments deserved fame, than all the gemmes or radiant stones in the Triple crowne or Spanish Diadem.</p>
            <p>And since the Prelates of late have been so presumptuously busie in melting base mettall, and casting their Canons, and mounting them so high as to batter down all Religion, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, fortifying their tottering holds of Episcopacy in the rearing againe the old ruines of Babell. Shall not the Lords servants be much more bold for Christ, than they for Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ? shall they fortifie and plant Canons contrary to both Lawes of God and of the Land, to batter downe our Religion and liberties, and shall not we reare our forts and plant Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of proofe by both Lawes, and play upon their Babell Building? long agoe, yea of old determined to destruction, as <hi>Jericho,</hi> and cursed they who shall attempt to reare its<note place="margin">Iosh. 6.</note> ruines againe.</p>
            <p>If ever were a time for Christs servants, as men of another spirit, to take courage and Camp about Babell; then now when she hath laid our Zion waste: high time for every faithfull ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of God, and loyall subject to be up and be doing, every one something within compasse of his calling. This is solely the Authors minde and ayme at this time in Conscience of his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, here representing to thy view, a new reard battery against Babells loftie fort of Prelacy, planted with ten new cast Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of old tryed mettall, playing upon their tottering building on all parts, from the highest pinacle to the ground-work and foundation: which is not onely sandy but laid in a filthy dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill, and wasting daily; so the servants of Christ may even hence be encouraged, that the downfall of it is feizible enough if they campe about it with courage and constancy, as the Israe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites about Jericho, and we shall see it fall suddenly with Shout and Cry.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:111535:4"/>
            <list>
               <head>The names of the Canons, and how they are planted and discharged.</head>
               <item>1 Canon ab alto fulminans, <hi>strikes downe right from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven fiery hot thunderbolts at their two high pinacles of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiepiscopall bla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>phemy.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 Canon lucis a meridie fulgens, <hi>payes them on the blinde side for they look South-east, Rome-ward, and are blinde South-ward, Sun-ward; their right eye is darkned and no light in them,</hi> Zach. 14. 17.</item>
               <item>3 Canon Regis Caroli Christi vindex, <hi>playes upon the corner stone of their building.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4 Canon John the Baptist ex officio suo, <hi>playes upon their breast-works.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5 Canon old Romane on the South-east, which way they look most for help, <hi>playes upon the maine bulk and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of their building, where all their treasure and baggage lyes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6 Canon Apostolick, <hi>in a running trench, closely batters the foundation round about on every side.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>7 Canon ex ore Christi eradicans, <hi>or Canon roote all, fires a myne which springs and scatters the ground-stones of the foundation.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>8 Canon gregis &amp; utrius{que} legis, <hi>or Canon clense all, from the honourable high Court of Parliament, runs round about their works, charged with great and small shott, sweeping out root and branches, and clensing the Land of all their remnants.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The next two Canons are planted upon their passage to cut off all ayde and succour from them, whiles the other are battering.</head>
               <item>9 <hi>Canon Minans,</hi> or stand of Assistants.</item>
               <item>10 <hi>Canon flagrans,</hi> a long Basiliske whose fiery eyes at long distance threatens death and destruction to all that come neare to plead for them, or partake with them against the Lord Iesus, the mighty King incensed to wrath against their working.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:111535:4"/>
            <p>And thus courteous Reader, if thou mindest aright this service, I hope thou shalt finde it not unprofitable at this time, but affording some usefull instructions to all sorts of men, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by tis hoped some may be bettered in some measure.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The first to be looked at are the suffering servants of God, who have lyen under long and great oppressions under the Prelates, these may hence be comforted, to see their long deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted cause at length victorious, though the scidge prove long, these Canons are strong, will not miscarry if the service be hot, nay if some of them be not discharged at all that depend on mens hands and handling, yet there are enough besides in the number that will not spare them, and are in the divine hand of a jealous God, who will let flie at them, one thunderclap from on high at their blasphemy, will teare their building from top to bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, or a word from the Lord Iesus mouth, shall roote them when he begins to roare in mount Zion, his voice is powerfull and full of majestie, <hi>Psal. 29. 4.</hi> he will shake their deepe roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and lay them on the ground; his eyes are as flames of fire if once his wrath begin to burne, woe to them he finds in his way of advancing his kingdome; he will make waste mountains and hills of greatest enemies, for the Lord is jealous, the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengeth, the Lord avengeth and is furious, the Lord will take vengeance on his enemies, <hi>Nahum 1. 2.</hi> and he will comfort Zion, and build her waste places, he hath had respect to the prayer of the desolate, and will not tarry, they may then be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, to them belongs the songs and palms of victory over the beast of Rome and his Image, in these bratts of Babell; these are they that come out of great tribulation, that keepe the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements and faith of Jesus, that are not defiled with the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinesse of the whorish woman, for they are the virgins that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Lambe, and shall enter with him through the gates in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Citie. The consideration whereof should mitigate their present sorrowes, having an eye to the recompence of reward.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The enemies of Christs kingdome may read their doome from the righteous judgement of the Lord of hoasts, and be at last provoked to repentance and resignation of their unlawfull offices, and doe homage to Christs Scepter, who otherwise will come as a thiefe in the night upon them, and cut off their pompe
<pb facs="tcp:111535:5"/> and power, and make them naked and unarmed, and cast them out as dogs out of the holy Citie; and so there be left them no place to repentance, though they seek it with teares, out of time, when the gate of the Kingdome is shut against them, they may howle, and cry, and knock till they be weary, ere S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>Peters</hi> keyes come to open. This will certainly befall them sooner or later, if they repent not.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Those that are gone back to the flesh-pots of Egypt, and are swimming downe with the streame of the time, may be fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned to returne, and come out of the tents of these wicked men, least by partaking in their sinnes, they partake of their plagues; for it is the time of the Lords vengeance, the yeare of<note place="margin">Isa.</note> recompence of the Controversies of Zion.</p>
            <p n="4">4. All sorts of men, loyall subjects of the King, and good Patriots of their Countrey, may be moved with pitty to helpe to remove the insupportable burthens which presse downe the land<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ʋbi dolor ibi digitus,</hi> is the part and dutie of every mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</note> to ruine and misery, all flowing from the Hierarchy: and till the pressures in Religion be removed, and Christs kingdome ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced, the Common-weale cannot be eased: they are like <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates</hi> twinns, they mourne and rejoyce, live and dye toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Tis the office of Prelacy that keepes out Christs kingly office, is the <hi>Achan</hi> sin that troubles the Land, and is the cause of all our miseries, and threatens still greater: if that be not removed, Gods wrath will not be appeased, our troubles not ended. The Lord pitty us, and ease himselfe and us of these his Adversaries, who will not have Christ to reigne over them.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>Undi{que} concurrunt ac crescit turba malorum,</l>
                  <l>sed cum probrosi castra superba tenent.</l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Lament. 5. 17, 18.</bibl> For this our heart is faint, our eyes are dimme, because of the mountaine of Zion which is desolate, the Foxes walke upon it.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111535:5"/>
            <head>SOME ARGVMENTS AND MOTIVES TO The finall Extirpation of the usurped unlawfull Government of the HIERARCHY. <hi>AS</hi> Having no foundation in the Scriptures, but meerly in that filthy dunghill the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non Law of the Popes Authoritie, and therefore Antichristian.</head>
            <div n="1" type="argument">
               <head>Argument I.</head>
               <p>THat Name which is onely proper to the Lord Jesus, is unlawfull, yea blasphemy for any man to assume. But so is the name Archbishop onely proper to the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, (1 <hi>Pet. 5. 4. Heb. 13. 20. Acts 3. 15. &amp;</hi> 5. 31.) the chiefe Shepheard and Bishop of our soules, 1 <hi>Pet. 2. 25. Ergo</hi> for any man to assume that name is unlawfull; yea blasphemy, and the blasphemer should be stoned to death, <hi>Levit.</hi> 24. 11. 14.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="argument">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>That office whose originall is not knowne is unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111535:6"/> But the originall of the office of Archbishop is not knowne: as the chiefe champion of Prelacy confesseth, <hi>Whit gift cont. Cartwright, pag.</hi> 351. And further, nothing can be said for the primacy of a Metropolitane Bishop, but what will as well maintaine the primacy of the Pope as universall Bishop of all the world. <hi>Ergo</hi> the office of an Archbishop is unlawfull.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="argument">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>That name and office which is unlawfull, and blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my for any man to assume, no Prince or humane power may lawfully give. But so is the name and office of Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop, as before. <hi>Ergo</hi> no Prince or humane power may lawfully give it to any man; and wee hope his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty when he is rightly informed, will explode the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of it: this is the very corner stone of their building, if this once faile, the whole fabricke will sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly tumble upon their heads. The Lord grant it, and put into the heart of our royall Soveraigne to execute his will upon these Bratts of <hi>Babell.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="argument">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <p>No officer in the Church is lawfull, who cannot prove his function from the word, as <hi>Iohn</hi> did when the Priests questioned him, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 20. 23. 25. But all these officers in the Hierarchy from the chiefe Metropolitant to the meanest Apparitour, are such as cannot prove their fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions from the word when they are questioned: their onely proofes are sulminations of Canons, censures, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communications, prisons, and fines, cutting of eares and noses and brands. <hi>Ergo</hi> unlawfull.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="argument">
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>Those officers whose names, offices, and practises are derived from Antichrist, and serve principally to uphold
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111535:6"/> and propagate his Kingdome, ought not to governe the Church the Spouse of Christ: who will not have her ruled by such as live by the vices of men, and hyre of whores, commutations of pennance, selling of sins and giving libertie to all licentiousnesse. But Archbishops, Diocesan Bishops, Deanes Archdeacons, Chancellours, Officialls, &amp;c. their names offices and practises are such; as in one word appeares in that they have their founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in that filthy dunghill of the Canon law, and thence their practises, <hi>Ex mero officio,</hi> are onely warranted to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold and propagate the Kingdome of Antichrist, and bring in Popery againe. Neither can any thing be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced for a Diocesan Bishop and Church, but from the same ground will arise an Universall Church and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop, they stand upon one Antichristian foundation, which makes the Prelates and their officers love the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists so well. <hi>Ergo</hi> they ought not to governe the Church the Spouse of Christ.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="argument">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <p>Those officers in the Church, whose offices and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment from the foundation and very nature of their offices, doe waste and overthrow the principall functions of the Church and offices of Christ, are not of Christ but of Antichrist. But such are the offices of Archbishops, Diocesan Bishops, &amp;c. and the rest of that rable. <hi>Ergo</hi> not of Christ but of Antichrist.</p>
               <p>The Major I suppose no sound Protestant will deny.</p>
               <p>The Minor proposition is that must abide all the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery from the lofty Prelacy, their forts and mounts of molehill authoritie; but in the skirmish, we shall finde them all in a confusion, flourishing their colours, and drawing forth and mounting their Canons, and playing and discharging upon their own Canon Law, as if they seemed to batter their owne foundation, (like cunning Fencers that make a flourish on the stage and seeme to knocke downe one another, but 'tis a point of art to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111535:7"/> maintaine the trade) but as soone as the fury is over, we shall finde them with their Canons drawne into their old fortification, and upon the next advantage in the field againe, and at their old work and battery, at the foundations of the Church with greater fury, (it being the very nature of their office so to doe) yea (if God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent not now by the diligent hand of this honourable Parliament) to mount their Canons and Canon Law to such a height, as to batter at the Royall Authoritie, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentary priviledges, and Subjects liberties, to make havock of all, and bring in and erect a papall forreigne Jurisdiction in this Land againe.</p>
               <p>There be two maine Branches of our Minor proposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">Two branches of the Minor.</note> that the offices and government of the Hierarchy, 1. from the foundation of, 2. from the very nature of their offices and government doe waste and overthrow the functions of the Church and offices of Christ, we will demonstrate.</p>
               <p>1. That it is founded in the Canon Law, what their<note place="margin">First branch.</note> offices are, and how to be exercised, in such practices as uphold and propagate the Kingdome of Antichrist, read <hi>Angelus de Clansio,</hi> and other Canonists, where you may see their warrant for their offices, and practices in their government: to which upon all occasions they have their recourse in any difficultie, and fetch their dark light in stead of the Scriptures. So as when a new Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, a new Archdeacon, or a new Chancellour comes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his new office like a fresh man, the inferiour officers that be old practicioners in that Law, must instruct him in any matter of difficulty falling out in his government, after that Law, by which all must be ordered: and that it is true that the Canon Law is the foundation of their offices and government. See a book compiled out of the Canon Law, and entituled; <hi>Reformatio Legum Ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticarem,</hi> Printed 1571, and now of late reprinted and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by Authoritie; and in he Preface of the said book it is confessed, that the Canon Law of Popish govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was still retained in <hi>England</hi> to that day, and so is to this.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:111535:7"/>
               <p>Now what this Canon Law is, appeares by the Law it selfe to be nothing else but the Lawes and Decrees of the Popes of Rome and their authoritie point blanck opposite to the Lawes of God in generall, and the Lawes of Christ (for governing his Church) in speciall, and to our Kings prerogative royall and lawes of the Land. And 'tis a wonder how this Canon Law, branded and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolished by so many Statutes and Acts of Parliament, should be suffered to be exercised in this Land without (as Lawyers say) the incurring of a <hi>Praemunire,</hi> being a Law of forreigne and Papall Jurisdiction, abolished by the Stat. of 4. <hi>Edw. 6. cap. 11. &amp; 1. Eliz. cap. 5. &amp; 5. Eliz. cap.</hi> 1. 23. and others. And how this usurped govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is growne to an insufferable height, overtopping all authoritie, religion and liberties, I leave to the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Lawes, and grave judgements of this honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Parliament.</p>
               <p>We come then to the second branch of our proposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;<note place="margin">Second branch.</note> that it is from the very nature of their offices, that they waste and overthrow the functions of the Church and offices of Christ, meerly from that their foundation and warrant (in the Canon Law) of their practices in all they doe in their offices, as before.</p>
               <p>Now the nature of every thing is best tryed and seene in the things which issue from it, as the proper works and actions of every function, springing from the roote and foundation, as giving Lawes for warrant and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission, so vigour and life for execution and from thence we shall see as in a Prospect through their practices (so warranted) into the nature of their offices, and whether they waste the Church and overthrow the offices of Christ or no.</p>
               <p>The principall functions of the Church are; 1. the<note place="margin">Foure maine functions of the Church.</note> word. 2. prayer. 3. Sacraments. 4. discipline; all which like the mother that old withered wrinckled faced whore of Rome, they have most foully adulterated and filthily polluted.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For the word 'tis the very nature of their offices,<note place="margin">1 The Word.</note>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:111535:8"/> flowing in through their so warranted practices, to mix and mingle it with mens inventions, and shut their eyes against the Scriptures brightnesse; tell one of these Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates of warrant from the word, and he will give you such a learned answer, as would make his horse breake his halter, if he knew how unmercifull his Master were to his beast, as to question what warrant he hath from the word to give him a peck of Oats. An argument from Scripture sets them all in a rage; such an antipathy there is between the word and the very nature of their offices. 2. They corrupt the word with false doctrines, from their Canons; Books of Articles and Homilies, writings and preachings, wherewith the Pulpits sound alowd throughout the Land. 3. Their offices are to cause the people drinke these troubled waters, or drive their backs to the wall. 4. They have turned the Ministery wholly into a Jewish-Popish Sacrificing Priesthood. 5. They set up a new kinde of reading-preaching, and suppresse sound preaching, silence and suspend the orthodox Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and fill their places with Metaphysicall cloudy-brain'd Humanists, Arminian <note n="*" place="margin">Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bancks.</note> and Popish fellowes, who usually stuffe their Sermons out of <hi>Aristotles</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thicks, and the Fryars Postills. 6. In stead of the word they set up Images, Crucifixes, Altars, and teaching Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, to stirre up the dull minds of men, against Christs prerogative and propheticall office, to which it belongs to teach his Church by his word and works, and not by mens inventions and works of mens hands. 7. They Pope-like corrupt the word with their stink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing breath, breathing forth for Scripture what they please, some are the Fathers, others the sonnes of the Church, and <hi>in summa</hi> the Church of themselves, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt themselves above the Scriptures, especially when they meet in the Convocation house, and have their Canons in casting, they make lawes above and against the word, and preach for them, &amp; punish the breach of them more than the breach of Gods Commandements. 8. By ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of their offices they assume a power to conferre holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111535:8"/> upon things and places, consecrate Churches, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, and places, and place holinesse in their superstitions and abhominations, as Altars, Altar-cringing, Jesus, and East-worshipping, &amp;c. Whereas the word alone hath power to sanctifie and make holy. Thus by bringing in the accursed thing of Romes Idolatry, they are become the <hi>Achans</hi> that trouble the Land. 9. Nature works so strongly in their offices, as you may now see it in their bold impudent faces, professing reconciliation of us to Rome, pronouncing them happy that shall be the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments to reconcile the petty seeming differences, and make us at one with their mother, but I hope before that be done they and their mother shall be both confounded, <hi>Jere.</hi> 50. 11, 12. For the light hath dazled them, the Sunne is gone downe, and the day is dark over them to make them confounded and ashamed, <hi>Zach. 14. 17. Mich.</hi> 3. 6, 7.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For Prayer, how doe they by their very office<note place="margin">2 Prayer.</note> professe and practice the corrupting of it, which as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cense should be purely offred, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. They, 1. fill the house of God with smoke of the strange fire of their ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominations of all sorts, new and old inventions, Letany and long-som service, said and sung, with yelling and chanting like the Priests of <hi>Baal,</hi> their old and new in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, fopperies, second Service, and corrupt prayers, all put together, as like the Masse as an apple is like an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renge. 2. By their offices, they ordaine Priests of the lowest of the people, to offer up their corrupt prayers, as dumbe Sir <hi>Iohns,</hi> ale-house-keepers, and generally vile persons, who like <hi>Elyes</hi> sonnes cause men to abhorre their offerings. 3. All this corruption in worship flowes out of the Canon Law, as the filthy fountaine through their offices, as the pipes to set it abroad to infect the world, and is preserved as in cisternes in the Canons and service-booke, the second maine basis whereupon Episcopacy stands in the dunghill Canon Law, which casts such a foule savour in the nosthrills of God, as we may admire his patience in suffering it so long, without sweeping it
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111535:9"/> and us all together away in some strange inundation of Judgement.</p>
               <p>Nothing but a flood of Justice and reformation will prevent his kindled anger against us, manifested of late in so many fearefull and prodigious signes and wonders, especially in and about Churches, as if he had pointed with his finger that there is his quarrell, one strange fire procuring another, and threatning yet greater if we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent not, reforme not.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For the Sacraments, how have they changed them<note place="margin">3 Sacraments.</note> into Sacrifices, witnesse their baptismall regeneration, kneeling at Sacrament, or bread-worship, wherein wee are beholding to <hi>Costerus</hi> the Jesuite for telling us their meaning right out, if Christ (saith he) were not really in the bread, our kneeling were worse and more grosse Idolatry than that of the Heathen. Thus they turne the Sacraments into propitiatory Sacrifices, to wash away sinne and conferre grace, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>x opere op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rato:</hi> and so the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward work of Gods Spirit banished, it would be too te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious to be more in particulars.</p>
               <p n="4">4. For discipline, the nature of the office shews it selfe<note place="margin">4 Discipline.</note> here most, as in the strongest pulse, working with all its might continually by their Canons and Canon Law au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to oppose and suppresse Christs Kingly office and government, to repaire and restore the ruinous king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Antichrist, and that <hi>Iudas</hi>-like, <hi>Antichrist</hi>-like under a feigned profession of friendship to Christ. 2. Their offices uphold the Popish Canon law govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which hath left us no footsteps of the Apostolike discipline, and kingly office of Christ, wholly swept away in the great deluge of Popery, and never yet restored as our first reformers aymed, which may appeare by the Preface to the commination in the common prayer-booke, and were enough to set all reformed Spirits on work to perfect what they in the infancy of reformation left undone or faw not clearly, being then newly risen out of the long darksome night of Popery, and how should their diligence shame our negligence in so bright
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111535:9"/> a Sun-shine of the Gospel as we have had since, and stirre up our spirits to search out and set up that primitive dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline they aymed at now above fourscore yeares agoe, which hath been so much disputed for, written for, and petitioned for at so many Parliaments, and been onely hindred by these Antichristian Prelates, whose office it is to justle Christ from his throne, untill the words of God be fulfilled <note n="*" place="margin">Apoc. 17. 19.</note>, because they know the setting up of his kingdome will be the downfall of theirs, they cannot stand together; therefore this hath been long their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster-peice, with all their craft and cunning to uphold their Papall government and tyranny by their Canons and Canon law, to crush all who have stood in their way to oppose them, and plead for Christs owne discipline, using them worse than Turkes would have done as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse the multitude of Ministers and people in prisons murthered, of thousands banished, of families scattered, and estates ruined for standing for Christs discipline. 2. The very nature of their office is to thirst after the blood of Gods servants; <hi>Where Antipas my faithfull mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr is slaine, there is Sathans throne, Apoc.</hi> 2. 13. Of this tyranny let one of themselves be witnesse, (out of whose mouth the Lord exacted this testimony) Prelate <hi>Vaughan</hi> in a speech to D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Morton</hi> long agoe, (now Prelate of <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resme</hi>) confessed that the persecution of these times were worse than in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, and gave reasons for it. Now let Prelate <hi>Morton</hi> speak how they are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased in his time and by him, or if he will not, it may be God may exact it of him sometime with more hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of conscience than any of his predecessors, because he sins against greater light and more warnings; yea let Prelate <hi>Ʋsher</hi> speak whether his hands be cleare of the bloody persecutions in <hi>Ireland</hi> of late, and if they will not, the earth shall discover her blood, and no more hide her slaine: the infection of the bloody office is growne to such a height as hath not left any one of them untain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted one way or other. 4. If they all should hold their peace, the stones will cry in their High Commissions
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111535:10"/> and Courts, their books and Court Records shall testifie to posterity of their tyranny in government. So as it hath been an old tryed Maxime of their Courts; <hi>That a good man makes a bad cause there:</hi> how hath the terrour of their Courts made many Ministers and people, like the figge-tree, cast their fruit before they felt the storme, upon the first puffe of winde of appearance of troubles, when they have heard and seene how other men have been crushed and undone by them <note n="*" place="margin">Vestigià ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</note>. The very sight of a Puritane (as they brand them) in their Courts, makes their blood rise and their spirits rage and swell as against the mortall ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of their Dominion. And if the Papists plot of a long intended bloody Massacre had prevailed and not of late from Heaven been prevented, I beleeve their white sleeves would have been dyed in our blood ere now: their dog-like appetite so hungers after the Puritanes blood, as the very nature of their office so to doe, and cannot be otherwise, for this is the fruit of the old withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red stock of Romes Hierarchy, and the longer this tree of Prelacy springing out of that root shall stand, it grows taller and stronger, from the nourishment it receives from the sap and root in the dunghill foundation of the Canon Law: and according to the nature of the soyle the fruit must be, and so of necessitie bring forth daily more bitter fruits to the Church of God, like apples of <hi>Sodome.</hi> 5. The brightnesse of divine truth in this point of discipline, hath so dazled the Prelaticall partie, that of late they have confessed the discipline of the Church of <hi>England</hi> to be the same with the Church of Rome; and yet they are either so modest as ashamed to have it called Antichristian, or els so impudent as to deny the Pope to be Antichrist; as whores and bawds love the gaine and pleasure of their filthy trade, but cannot endure the name. What a shame is it to our Religion and Nation, to uphold Antichrists filthy trade and government, the mother of all abhominations, and mistresse of whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes; a thing so scandalous to all the reformed world of Protestants. 6. Let our deare friends and exiles in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merica</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:111535:10"/> speake, and the whole Kingdome at home of the scattered families of Christs servants, witnesse what ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vock they have made of the Church; and what rule they keep in Court and Countrey, Towne and Citie, from the Metropolitane to the meanest son of the Church, how they pierck and pranse it, above all Nobilitie and Gentry, and become the onely brave fellows and <hi>fac totums,</hi> in all affaires in the Common-weale as well as in the Church. So as at length they have over-shadowed the whole State, Eclipsed the very royall Authoritie, hindred the Sun-shine of his Princely aspect from his loyall subjects, and which is not the least of all, by the mists of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions and smoak of their superstitions abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, arising out of their sulphurious Seas, like the Asphal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites, they darken the light of the sun of Righteousnesse, and hinder us of the Lord Jesus his beautifull and shining rayes and influence of his sweet countenance, which like the Sun in his strength, would revive all our droopings, and make the Land to flourish, when once his throne, his rest were set up amongst us. O how would he make his rest glorious, <hi>Isa.</hi> 11. 10.</p>
               <p>Thus at last to conclude this argument, we have found in the office of Prelacy, the principall markes of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ; corrupt doctrine, corrupt worship and tyranny in government; all naturally flowing through their offices out of the same dunghill foundation with Antichrist; for if it were not in the nature and power of their offices thus to doe, their kingdome would long agoe have falne and come to nothing.</p>
               <p>And therefore the Prelates are wrongfully blamed for abusing their offices, the very nature and right use where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is to wast and overthrow the Church and offices of Christ, to overturne Kingdomes and Lawes, to propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate the kingdome of Antichrist; the office is so bad they cannot use it otherwise, no more than one of them can ride a horse blind and lame of all leggs, over mountaines and hills, without hazard of his neck: the office of Epis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy is the blind and lame Jade which they are moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111535:11"/> upon to over-ride all divine and humane authoritie, and will certainly breake their necks ere long; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the best office their friends can doe them, is to stop their gallopping, and to save their necks helpe to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount them.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Ob.</label> This cannot be so, will some say, why should the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates be so venturous, or ride so madly, they sure have a more care of themselves, than so desperately precipitate themselves to fatall ruine.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Ans.</label> Because they ride for a better horse, whence they had this, which makes them so loath to part with the Jade, and rather will venture a fall: every Priest rides for a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonage, every person for a Prebendary, every Prebend for a Deanery, so for a Bishoprick, an Archbishoprick, a Cardinallship, till some of them that ride fastest at last be mounted on mens shoulders, to make Princes run at their stirrup. Complaine not then of the Prelates abuse of their offices in trampling upon you, when it is the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the beast, and ride he must: if you would be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed of your paine, dismount the rider, and knock the lame Jade on the head.</p>
               <p>And thus we see how under a pretence of love to Christ, they overthrow all his offices, as Prophet, Priest, and King, and therefore the conclusion stands firme, that they are not of Christ, but of Antichrist: and then our next Argument tells us what will be the end of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="argument">
               <head>Argument VII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Every plant which my heavenly Father hath not planted, shall be rooted out,</hi> Mat. 15. 13. The Prelacy and their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices are no plants of the Fathers planting. <hi>Ergo</hi> they shall be rooted out, and as an abhominable branch (of the old withered stock of Romes Hierarchy be cut downe and cast out of the Church) as the garments of the slaine, (thrust through with the sword of authoritie) and as a carcasse trod under foote, <hi>Isa.</hi> 14. 19.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:111535:11"/>
               <p>The Major proposition is undeniable, being out of his mouth who is faithfull and true, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 13. 14. and will make it good in his own time, for out of his mouth goes a two edged sword, the sword of his Spirit, sharpening and thrusting forth the sword of the Magistrate, which in due time he will cause to be forbished and made bright to the slaughter of these his enemies, who will not have him to rule over them, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19. 17.</p>
               <p>The Minor is their part to prove. See Argument 4. And if they have any Letters Patents for their offices, let them open their black boxes and produce them, or els as polluted be put from the Priesthood, as those, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 7. 64. that could not reckon up their Genealogie from <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi.</hi> 2. In all the book of God from the beginning of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesis</hi> to the end of the <hi>Apocalyps,</hi> we find not one word of warrant for the name or office of an Archbishop, Dioce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>san Bishop, Deane, Archdeacon, Chancellour, or any of their orders, but are meerly derived from Antichrist, crept into the Church by carnall policy and flattery, and abuse of Princes favours, and have no foundation but in the Canon Law of the Pope, as before, <hi>Arg.</hi> 5. and 6. thats all the divine authoritie they have, and no wonder if it be divine enough for them to stand upon, being the same with Antichrist; for Diocesan Bishops were the first step whereby the Papacy mounted to its height, and are the pillars of its support even to this day. But when the Prelates father their authoritie, some upon God the Father, some upon God the Sonne, and others upon the holy Ghost, they declare themselves to be of that stamp Christ reproves and accuses of blasphemy, and to be of the Synagogue of Sathan, who say they are Jewes and are not but doe lye, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 3. 9. Who say they are A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles and are not, but are found lyers, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2. 2. So then when they boast of divine authoritie, they are right like themselves, for that is another mark of Antichrist, the adding of lyes to all their abhominations, for which they shall be cast out of the holy Citie, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 22. 15.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The whole streame of truth flowing out of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111535:12"/> Scriptures, as the fountain runs so strongly against them that down they goe to the Sea of Rome, that dead Sea, to fetch their pedigree from that ancient family of long Enmitie to Christ, the Ancient of dayes, and fountaine of all Antiquitie, before whom nothing was, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out whom nothing was made or done, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 2, 3.</p>
               <p>That this is so, see clearly M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Paul Baine</hi> his diocesan tryall, the very Prelates rats-bane, and will burst them ere long; it savours so sweetly of the Scriptures fragrant fulnesse and excellency by the breathings of Gods Spirit (which is the Prelates deadly poyson) that none of them durst ever take it in hand to answer it, now about twenty years published; and there who will may read the doome of their divine authoritie.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If they flie to Antiquitie, we ans. 1. We acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge no antiquitie, but what is according to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, the Judge of all Controversie; its a sure rule of the learned against the Papists, that <hi>Whatsoever is not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Word, but by or besides the Word is against the Word.</hi> 2. We answer with <hi>Cyprian</hi> the flowre and swee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test bloome of all antiquitie, a Martyr and a Bishop, but no Lord, or Diocesan Bishop. <hi>Epist. ad Pomp. Epist.</hi> 74. Antiquitie without truth, is antiquitie of errour, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie without truth is nothing worth saith our learned <hi>Whitakers, Controvers de Eccles. quaest.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>But to leave them more without excuse, we will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secute yet one tryall more of them, which we learne from our great Master the Lord Jesus, for the discovery of false Prophets, who come in sheepes cloathing, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly are ravening Wolves, <hi>By their fruits yee shall know them,</hi> Mat. 7. 15, 16, 20. False Prophets in Scripture al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes set forth such as have no lawfull but a pretended office, so the Diocesan Bishops, &amp;c. are the false Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets wee have to doe withall; the name of Prophets, so the name of Bishops is the sheeps cloathing they come in to doe the works of Sathan and Antichrist; the very name of Bishop (which in it selfe is good) is like <hi>Jacobs</hi> voice with <hi>Esaus</hi> hands, theres much power of Sathan
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111535:12"/> used under the shelter of words and names, as of great force to deceive, Mountebanck-like, and therefore saith<note place="margin">Luther. de fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so nom. &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine Episcopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. Tom. 2. p. 330.</note>
                  <hi>Luther,</hi> they shew or set out themselves as if they were Pastours of the Church, as if they were Bishops, when they are meere shadowes, sacrificing persons, dumb sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and painted truncks, under the loftie high title of Bishops, destroying the whole world: and therefore ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been too long deceived with words and names, wee now will follow Christs rule, <hi>By their fruits to know them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The office of Prelacy, is the lame Jade we spoke of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven now, and hath been long tryed by the Word, but now is growne so hot ridden, as will not abide that kinde of handling, therefore the last tryall of them is this, <hi>By their fruits to know them,</hi> and so by their footsteps we shall see which way they are running.</p>
               <p>Now the fruits of the office, wee have shewed in the foregoing Argument to be the overthrowing of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of Christ, and propagating the Kingdome of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ, <hi>Ex mero officio,</hi> as the proper fruits of their functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and naturally flowing through the office out of that filthy lake of Romes authoritie (as before) and therefore the fruits must needs be according to the soyle, bitter fruits to the Church of God. And here wee will take a further tryall of them, and how they grow and increase in fruitfulnesse.</p>
               <p>Such plants as are of the Fathers planting; the Son purgeth that they may bring forth more fruit, <hi>Ioh. 15. 2. Fruits unto holinesse,</hi> Ephes. 4. 24. But we see when these men once enter into a Bishops Sea, or other their offices, they soone wither and cast their fruit; how many of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and good abilities, before they entred into these cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt offices have quickly after fallen under the withering curse of the Fig-tree, <hi>Never fruit grow more upon thee.</hi> And how can it be otherwise, theres such a plaguy infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction lyes in the office arising out of the filthy dunghill foundation, which rots and blasts all the fruits of their learning and morall parts, and renders them wholly like
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111535:13"/> the soyle they live in, and corrupt ayre of the Episcopall Seas they breath in: heres the infection, the poyson that kills them sooner or later; tis in the office, not so much in the person, but as the office infects him; therefore no safetie to their persons till they be put out of the infected places to lodge in fresh ayre. Their counsell then is not<note place="margin">A Caveat.</note> good who would onely remove and change the persons, and put other learned men in the places. O it is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test cruelty you can doe to these mens soules, you had better place them to live in a Pest-house, or cast their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies alive into the <hi>Mari Mortuo,</hi> than into a Bishops Sea, if they be good men they should so save their soules, whereas this way you hazard their soules and bodies both. Let none then be so cruell to their friends, to put them upon this preferment on so desperate a condition, wherein its as possible for them to bring forth good fruit as for an Apricock to grow in a dunghill. Wee have Christs assurance for it, <hi>A corrupt tree cannot bring forth good fruit;</hi> the tree still signifies the office not the person, for its spoken of false Prophets, and tryall of them by their fruits; <hi>Doe men gather grapes on thornes, or figges on thistles,</hi> still shewes it to be the office of those false Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, where Christ never ordained any good fruits to grow, and therefore none to be expected, but of a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt tree corrupt fruit; <hi>Therefore every tree which brings not forth good fruit, shall be hewen downe and cast into the fire,</hi> Mat. 7. 16. to 20. This good fruit as wee shewed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven now is <hi>fruit unto holinesse.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We will try then the fruits of this tree of Episcopacy, and the severall branches of its offices, and we finde them all taste of the dunghill soyle, they are rooted in and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their proper nourishment from, and are no <hi>fruits unto holinesse:</hi> For wee doe finde by wofull experience, that the fruits of their offices and government hath filled the Land with all prophanenesse, and sinning with gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinesse in all licentiousnesse, and therefore unholy offices, an unholy government, which not onely countenance sincks of sin and wickednesse, but live in and are main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:111535:13"/> by the vices of men, as the hire of whores, selling of sinnes and filthinesse, commutations of pennance, and oppressions of his Majesties Subjects, and disabling them for King and Countryes service. This is the chiefe main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of their offices, which if once, with the Canon Law that warrants these practices, were taken away, we should quickly see this great Amphitheater of Prelacy moulder downe and fall into the dunghill from whence it arose, and then one faire flood of Justice from this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Parliament, would soone sweep away all the filth together, and clense the Land of these corrupt and contagious offices.</p>
               <p>The seats of their offices, their Cathedrall Cities and Pallaces are very dennes of all filthinesse and prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, the most uncleane birds in the Countrey resort to dwell under their shadow, as having there libertie to live in all licentiousnesse. The name of <hi>holinesse</hi> there, is as a Jew to an Egyptian an abhomination; their Abbeyes, Deaneries and Episcopall Seas, are like the <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>phaltites,</hi> pitchy sulphurious Lake, nothing that savours of or breaths holinesse can live there. Their Courts and Judgements-seats are so many batteryes against holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, thundering and flaming out fire and smoke from their Canons and murthering pieces, at the very name of (or persons that looke after) holinesse, as the mortall enemies of their dominion and government, against which if a man let the least word fall, presently <hi>ex officio</hi> excommunicate him, <hi>ipso facto,</hi> ere he stirre from them, he shall not have a warning peace to be gone, but a whole battery of Canons discharged upon him, in such heate and rage, fire and smoke of their fulminations, as he shall scarce know what ground he stands on, till for change of ayre he be hald away to a stincking prison, to complaine to the bare-walls. Oh if he be a Puritane, thats condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation in the abstract, enough to rid the Land of him, yea the world too, if they get their opportunitie.</p>
               <p>And for their language in the exercise of their offices, they speak half in the language of Ashdod, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 13. 24.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111535:14"/> like the mingled people, <hi>Jere.</hi> 50. 37. of many religions, yea of any save the true, because thats no friend to them, and their functions.</p>
               <p>But because they boast so much of their descent from Christ and his Apostles, but are found lyers, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2. 2. We will (by their leave) take a walke further through their Orchards, and taste of their ripest fruits, and try what soyle they taste of, whether the fruits of the functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Christ and his Apostles, or of Antichrists functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and offices.</p>
               <p n="1">1. When Christ was to leave his deare Disciples in a troublesome world, he left his peace with them for a Legacy, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15. 27. to comfort them in all their trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and commands them to love one another, because the world would hate them, as it hated him, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15. 17. But these Prelates by their vexatious offices, suffer Christs Ministers and servants to have little peace, and lesse love, hate them <hi>Cain</hi>-like, even to the death; but a Papist is a brave companion for them, at Table, in Coach, in coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell and familiaritie, in all their affaires; as <hi>Blackwell</hi> the Priest said long agoe, I wonder, said he, of what religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your Bishops are, us they persecute because we are Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists, but they hate a Puritane, and of the two, they love us the better: and how that love is encreased, shews they are birds of the black feather, (like the Raven that after she once got out of the Arke never returned) so, as soone as ever one of these Prelates is got into a Bishops Sea, they are flowne out of the Church, the infection of the fowle nest like the plague of Leprosie, strikes them, some sooner, some later, so as they take to their wings and flie home to Rome, the resting place of their ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous minds, and who can blame them (for it is the nature of the office, to be like and love their mother) and not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther help them forward to her.</p>
               <q>Sic canibus catulos similes sic matribus haedos. <note place="margin">Virgil.</note>
               </q>
               <p>Of this their flight to Rome, see it clearly in their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:111535:14"/> of reconciling us to their Mother, and others of them not so skilfull in the art, as forward in the flight, labouring openly to reduce us wholly to Rome, <hi>Ex pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesso tanquam ex officio,</hi> as the very nature of the office so to doe, to beget and bring forth many children to their mother, ther's some plaine dealing in these if they doe not turne with the winde, which now troubles them in their flight and work. For as birds nodding their heads, let us see which way they are flying, so the Prelates and their sonnes of the Church by their nodding Eastward, let us see their ayme is Rome-ward. And when in this late Episcopall quarrell with the <hi>Scots</hi> by their sole insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, they saw a necessitie of open flight to the Popes and Papists ayde, or lose their fat Bishopricks, expecting this faire season for their flight, they were so ready for it, as they had their excuses ready before hand. [That if Popery came into <hi>England</hi> againe, the Puritanes were the cause of it <note n="*" place="margin">Prelate of <hi>Duresme.</hi>
                  </note>] as <hi>Tentorton</hi> Steeple is the cause of <hi>Goodwin Sands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Christ would not meddle with the Magistrates au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie in dividing the Inheritance, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 13, 14. as without compasse of his office, his kingdome was not of this world, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 18 36. These Prelates are wholly world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, must be chiefe in Parliaments, in the Kings Councells, in chiefe offices, Lord Chancellour, Lord Treasurer, &amp;c. and oversway all the affaires in Court and Countrey, as if by their pretended divine Authoritie, they had full Commission from Christ to divide the world amongst them, and Pope-like challenge all the Kingdomes of the world, and the ends of the Earth for a possession, from <hi>Psal.</hi> 2. Thus like Foxes on the mountaines, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13. 4. on mountaines of prey (<hi>Psal.</hi> 76. 4.) mounted in their High Commissions and Courts, like to the Mountaines of Leopards, <hi>Cant.</hi> 4. 8. they prey upon all that come neare them; fine and imprison, and cease on mens lands and estates, and divide many an Orphans inheritance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>John</hi> the Baptist the greatest Prophet bome of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:111535:15"/>
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 7. 28. his cloathing was but course, <hi>Camells haire and a letherne girdle about his loynes,</hi> his dyet but homely, <hi>Locusts and wilde honey,</hi> Mat. 3. 4. These Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates ruffle it bravely in silks and velvets, and pure Lawne sleeves, like Butchers ever ready to have their hands in blood, and the meanest son of the Church must have a silken girdle with a rose up to his nose, as if his pride were his perfume, and for his dyet it must be dainty fare, no Butchers meate, Pheasant and Venison for their weake stomacks (opprest with studies but of what kind? <hi>Quaere</hi>) washt downe with the most delitious wines. As they! so their Prebends must keepe residence at the Bishops Sea, (but not at their Parishes) to feast the Clergie while the flockes are starving with cold service of a S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
                  <hi>Iohn. Whose belly is their God, whose glory their shame, who minde earthly things,</hi> Phil. 3. 19. Of whom that of the Monkes of old is verified.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>O monachi vestri st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>machi sunt amphora bacchi,</l>
                  <l>Vos estis deus est testis turpissima pestis.</l>
               </q>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Paul</hi> accounted all things losse for the excellency of the knowledge of Christ, and counted them but dung, and for to gaine Christ suffered the losse of all things, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 8. These Prelates account all gaine they by their offices gather, and pick out of mens purses by fines and taxes and illegall courses to gaine Antichrist. Witnesse <hi>Pauls,</hi> and such like good works they cry up, to make gorgeous Temples, nests for Idolls, Images, Altars, Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifixes, and rich Ornaments, baits and allurements to carnall sense, to draw the ignorant to their mothers for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications in her old rotten age. And for losse, before they will lose any thing of their dignitie to gaine Christ, they will hazard the losse of Christ and all these three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to Rome and Spaine or France.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Peter</hi> calls <hi>Paul, Beloved brother:</hi> these like Spanish Donns, must be called of their brethren, My Lord, your Grace, and Right reverend Fathers, and be bowed to like Princes.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:111535:15"/>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Peter</hi> is content to stoop so low as to write himselfe in the lowest style belonging to his function, <hi>An Elder, 1 Pet.</hi> 5. 1. These on the contrary assume the highest styles of Earles in their writing; as <hi>Will: Cant, Tho: Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resme, Jos: Exon.</hi> Exonored of his spectacles in his old dayes, for he hath eyes for other men to see with, but it is at blinde man buff. But thankes be to God we can see so much with our owne eyes, that they are begun to fall, when <hi>Jos: Exon</hi> is fallen so low, as from a Father to a son of the Church, with the meanest Priest, as having too long lorded it over his brethren.</p>
               <p n="7">7. We are commanded to feare God, honour the King, and meddle not with them that are given to change, <hi>Pro.</hi> 24. 31. These Prelates are so Cock-sure in their warme nests as in the clefts of the Rocks, that they shew little feare of God or his revenging Justice, as if they had writ over their gates, Mock God, Mock Devill, Babel-like at defiance with both; <hi>I sit as a Queene and shall never be moved,</hi> Isa. 47. Apoc. 18. And as the Spaniard had writ over the gates of the <hi>Buss</hi> in <hi>Brabant</hi> or <hi>Boss-le due,</hi> this blasphemous Inscription, <hi>When the Buss is taken God shall be a lyar;</hi> as I have heard of credible hands; but God made the <hi>Hollander</hi> blot out that blasphemy, &amp; left them lyars. 2. For honour of the King, they so farre observe it as their own honour is concerned, and in the first place regarded, the other must but serve it. 3. And because they have not honour enough, or be high enough, they are busie medling with Papists and Jesuites, the great ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists of the world for changes of Kings and Kingdomes and States, turning them up-side downe, to change our Lawes, our Religion, and liberties, and lives too; and to plant the Land with Spaniards, as we had found ere now, if the Spanish Fleet last yeare had once landed, but blessed be God, who without us prevented it, and broke that devillish designe, and gives us faire warning to take heed to such Prelates, so officious in their offices, whose na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture sures so with the Jesuites, alwayes digging under ground and working changes. They have sucked all the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:111535:16"/> nourishment to higher advancement that this State can afford them, and so full ripe for a Miter and a Cardinalls cap, which here are not, that tis high time they were gone where they may have them, rather than they bring Rome and Spaine to us to obtaine them.</p>
               <p>These are a taste of some of their ripest fruits we finde as yet, though doubtlesse others may finde many moe, but blessed be God who hath a little shaken their fruits that now our hoggs doe eate them.</p>
               <p>Yet certainly Right Honourable Worthies now as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled in Parliament, if this tree of Episcopacy none of Gods planting, but a plant of Sathans planting, sprung up in the dunghill of the Papacy, naturally bringing forth these bitter fruits, be of you suffered to stand but till ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther solstice of warme Sun-shine come over from Rome or Spaine, wee shall finde more dangerous and deadly fruits of it ere long, <hi>Acherontam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vendo.</hi> What mischiefes will they not hatch ere they lose their gainfull offices, their pleasant loftie dignities: will never be content in a lower condition; nay, before they quit their ground, as stout Souldiers and Champions of the Romish Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, they will be busie under ground with the Jesuites, the chiefe Masters of fire-works, to spring a mine of some horrid plot of a new invention, to make all these three Kingdomes shake: as some of their excommunicate bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of <hi>Scotland</hi> bolted out of late; alas their hearts were so heavy as they must vent some wind rather than burst. Are not these brave Spirits will venture upon such hard service for their Master? The King of Spaine we heare stands in need of such artists to blow up the walls of Lis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone, tis pitty he should want them.</p>
               <p>And therefore Right Honourable, bestirre your selves betime to meete those underminers with a countermine, to spring them and their works together: theres no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way of safetie to our King and his posteritie, and all these three Kingdomes, so linked together in so many bands, as we must of necessitie stand and fall together. I love to speak plaine English, and think none will blame
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:111535:16"/> me of temeritie or rashnesse at this time, but such as speak too much Spanish. I doe but the office of a Beacon, which is <hi>Monstrare, non ducere nec docere,</hi> to shew the approaches of dangers, if you prevent not. Men use not to blame him who lyes Sentinel <hi>perdue</hi> as a lost man, for giving warning of danger.</p>
               <p>Though now it might seeme we have enough of the Prelates windie divine authoritie, now found none of Gods planting, as by their fruits at Christs command we have tryed and found them: and therefore nothing now wanting, but the execution of his own sentence, to be rooted out, which we now expect by the diligent hand of this Honourable Parliament. Yet may I not passe till I have met with <hi>Tho: Duresme</hi> in particular, because he hath deceived many, both Papists and Protestants in their expectations, and by his leave, I would faine love my Religion and Countrey above his dignitie or regali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, more fit for one of the Kings Sons than any Prelate, and therefore for his cause we will have one bout more about the office.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="argument">
               <head>Argument VIII.</head>
               <p>Those offices and that government in the Church, which nourish ignorance and blindnesse, an idle, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and unsound Ministery, persecute our Religion e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stablished, and the orthodox Preachers and professors of it, and cherish and countenance Popery and Papists, and their dangerous meeting and Masses, are not of Christ, but of Antichrist. But such are the offices and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Diocesan Bishops and the rest of that rable. <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go</hi> not of Christ but of Antichrist.</p>
               <p>The Major if they will cavill at here, see it made good <hi>Arg.</hi> 6. And so we proceed to the proofe of the Minor; which if it be all made good in the office and officers of <hi>Tho: Duresme,</hi> accounted one of the best in the bunch, it may be worth something, to move the rest in modesty to take it home to them without more adoe.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:111535:17"/>
               <p n="1">1. For ignorance and blindnesse, an ignorant idle and unsound Ministery, persecution of Religion established, and the orthodox preachers and professors of it, though too conformable, his diocesse and government may bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter challenge the Metropolitane precedency, than his kingly regalitie: none of them, not <hi>Will. Cant.</hi> or the winged little <hi>Wren,</hi> hath flowne more swiftly home to Rome in their practises, at least he may deserve the place next to them, none of them hath so scorned their Seas of sound Preachers, (as if they were Pirates to the Prelates office) as he hath done, so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>se few puritane Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers (as they terme them) whom his worse reputed predecessors, had left in that Diocesse, and some others brought in by men well affected to preaching in that poore ignorant Countrey, (an object of this honourable Parliaments pitty) he hath had the honour to root them out. So as in one poore County of Northumberland and towne of Newcastle, in about seventy two or more Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishes (besides Chappells) whereof divers livings of two three and foure hundred <hi>per annum,</hi> as we are credibly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by some of the Inhabitants of credit, ther's scarce a Minister left that is not a superstitious innovator, or not popish, and Arminian, or that make conscience of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, but as they please at their leasure, or regard the peoples soules, but prey upon their fleeces, and poll their purses, like soule-murtherers, as <hi>Augustin</hi> calls them.<note place="margin">August. de pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>store.</note> And some Gentlemen who have been at the charge of keeping godly Preachers, have been robd of them by these Wolves ravening, that lay waste Countryes and Congregations; such rule he keepes. If <hi>Tho: Duresme</hi> house were so kept as he hath kept Gods, there would be nothing but hungar and hard walls, and cold entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for his fat Prebends: and who knows but the Lord may ere long send as much famine amongst them, as they have had feasting, and the poore flocks starving. And for his County Palatine of <hi>Duresme,</hi> that soyle can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not beare sound preaching and Preachers, no plants for his Palatinate, but if you will talke of fat parsons and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonages,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:111535:17"/> fat Prebends, pluralists, and tot quots, &amp;c. his soyle affords as good store of these fat Cattle, like kine of <hi>Bashan</hi> (as it doth of fat Oxen) nestling in fat livings of foure, five, six, and seven hundred pound <hi>per annum,</hi> and as full stall-fed as any in the Land: most of which livings have been of late supplyed by his kinsmen and others his friends, brought in by him into chiefe offices, popish and superstitious, of D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Cozens</hi> garbe, so as he hath outgone his predecessors herein. In summa, <hi>Will: Cant.</hi> or little <hi>Wrenns</hi> diocesses cannot paralell his, for a crue of dumbe doggs, Sir <hi>Iohns;</hi> alehouse-keepers, prophane antick fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, more fit for a stage than a pulpit, and other popish Arminian Mountebancks, that vend the Italian wares as fast as any in the Land. So that in this particular, he is the greatest soule-murtherer in the Land without the mountaines of <hi>Wales,</hi> woe will be to him for it; and for oppression, and Inclosures, &amp;c. his poore Palatines say, that their case is little better than the poore <hi>Irish</hi> Cram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macrees under the Lord Lieutenant.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For Superstition, let his Cathedrall and Sea of <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> witnesse, and be visited, it will be found as well fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered as the <hi>Wrens</hi> nest: and for <hi>Tho. Duresme</hi> himselfe, he is so zealous of Altar-worship, and such fopperies, as before he misse of his devotion, he will duck to a Tombe, in stead of an Altar, its good to be sure.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For countenancing Popery, and cherishing Papists, his Chancellour, Archdeacon, and Officialls, in riding their Circuits, make these their chiefe familiars: but for puritanes, they tosse and tumble them in their Courts, till they be wearied our of their callings, and Countrey too, <hi>Tho: Duresme</hi> himselfe threatning to rid the Land of them, till then, saith he; it will never be at rest. And if the times had not suddenly turned above all humane ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, its most probable by many prodigious signes, that the first bloody massacre of all that but favoured our religion as well as the puritanes, should have begun in his<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Newcastle</hi> be thankfull to God, thou hast scap't a scour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging.</note> Diocesse, in Northumberland, and towne of <hi>Newcastle,</hi> full stuft with his palatine Papists, it seemes, to that end,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:111535:18"/> and those of the most dangerous in the Land, never mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lested till the <hi>Scots</hi> scattered them.</p>
               <p>The said <hi>Tho: Duresme</hi> amongst his palatine Souldiers, most Papists, in these late Episcopall broyles, was obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to have in his Coach with him one of the most dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Papists in the North, &amp; fit to be one of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Warre in his regalitie, and in that Episcopall quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell with the <hi>Scots;</hi> which being publickly taken notice of, was very offensive to many, and scandalous to his Majesties government, and to his pretended divine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, to see <hi>Tho: Duresme</hi> so accompanied: I know not what he can say to this, but that he left his Rochet and office at his Sea of <hi>Duresme,</hi> and now in his regalitie no more Bishop; as the Lutherane Priests in Germany, when they goe to a feast, lay downe their black gowne, saying, Lie thou there Priest, now Ile be as joviall as the best of you: so <hi>Camelion</hi>-like change into any colour.</p>
               <p>He also nourishes in his Diocesse a company of popish-Arminian Ministers, of <hi>Wil: Cant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> chiefe correspondence, by whom (as by the like in other parts of the Land) he hath had constant intelligence of all matters, and of all the persons and families that favour our religion in those parts, that once they might get a day to rid the world of them.</p>
               <p>He also connives at dangerous meetings of the most stirring Papists, their baptismes and night burialls, with tapers, and torches, and bells ringing, but without the use of the Service Booke, and against their owne Canons: whereby it appeares, their Service Booke and Canons serve onely against puritanes, and must not be discharged against Papists. So as the chiefe Townes of his diocesse, are of late become dennes of Papists, and places of resort to their meetings and Masses, and of traffique and trade in their Books and Beads and Romish Merchandize.</p>
               <p>All which considered, he may be said to have given the lye to all his former works and writings against the Papists. So that it may be verified of him, that he is the greatest Papist friend that ever came in <hi>Duresme</hi> since our
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:111535:18"/> reformation. See here how the Antichristian office hath blasted all his fruits, and made him the shame of his old age, and of that pretended divine office of Episcopacy, which now the Lord will have made naked to the world. And all this flowes out of the dunghill foundation and filthy nature of the office, serving principally to propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate Antichrists kingdome, to waste the Church and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow the offices of Christ. So as it would seeme that Episcopacy now is come to its full height and ripenesse in this Land: it hath ever since our reformation opposed Christs kingly office, as its mortall enemy, whereby its growne to this height at this day to overthrow his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall and Priestly offices also: that all the world may see, as in the Sun-shine, that the offices and government of the Prelacy, are meerly Antichristian.</p>
               <p>By this time, I thinke, they have done, and so have we with their divine Authoritie, as having too long raked in that dunghill, and therefore we come now to the issue. That since they cannot reckon up their genealogie from <hi>Levie,</hi> (from another divine authoritie than the Canon Law) let them as polluted be put from the Priesthood, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 7 64. Thus did good <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and the Princes, true patternes of reformation before us. The Lord put into the hearts of his Majestie, and the Worthies of this Honourable Parliament, to follow their example, and to clense the Land of this polluted Priesthood and filthy dunghill offices of Antichristian Authoritie, which hath so long eclipsed the Gospels light, and the name and fame of our Nations glory in the eyes of all the reformed world, who with the bulk and body of Popery, have also cast off this heavie yoke and regiment of Episco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy.</p>
               <p>Therefore as not compatible with Christs kingly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and scepter of his Word, with Our royall Kings Authoritie, our Sions peace, and Kingdomes glory in the flourishing of Christs Kingdome. Wee hope this Honourable Parliament, will no longer suffer this tree of Sathans planting to stand, but root it out, according
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:111535:19"/> to Christs owne sentence and will, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17. 16. 20. and<note place="margin">Away with all the reverend Fathers, and their sonnes of the Church, with all their trumpery.</note> 15. 13. Cut off from <hi>Babell</hi> roote and branch, son and nephew, name and remnant, destroy her utterly, let no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of her be left, <hi>Ier. 50. 26. Isa.</hi> 14. 22. thinke it not to be sufficient (for you will not finde it so) to curbe the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solency, and lop off the loftie spreading branches of this tree of Episcopacy, when the Lord Jesus hath said it shall be rooted out, and hath laid the axe of his Word to the roote, and will have it cut downe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. 10. and <hi>cap. 17 20. and cast into the fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doe you Right Honourable and Noble workmen of the Lord, take it as a choise blessing, that now the Lord hath by a Parliament put into your hands the axe of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, to be also layd to the root of this tree, and count it your greatest honour, every one of you, to lend it a blow, and it will suddenly fall; God hath done his part, if you set to yours, he will put strength into your hands against all difficulties; be strong and of good courage,<note place="margin">Iosi. 1. 9.</note> these Cananites shall be but bread for you, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14. 9. for the Lord is with you: to remove mountaines of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties that lye in your way, if yee faithfully trust to his assistance, yee shall say to these mountaines, remove and they shall be cast into the Sea, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21. 22. Plow up the very roots, and weed the ground, the land of it, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it be left, and the place will be a fruitfull soyle. Their pluralities and fat Livings they have enclosed and impaled to serve their ease, their pomp and pleasures, will be as Sharon, Sheepfolds for Christ to feed his flocks by his Shepheards tents, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1. 8. Therefore doe not this work of the Lord negligently; if you curbe their greatnesse and lop the branches never so much, and leave the root, the office in the ground, within their warme nests and Episcopall Seas, though you shall binde it downe with Iron bands, and lay upon it all the weight of good Lawes you can possibly devise, it will through the sent of the puddle water, bud and spring againe next<note place="margin">Iob 14. 9.</note> season, and bring forth more bitter fruits than ever: Episcopacy, (not the persons is the root of all our evills)
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:111535:19"/> it is that uncleane bird we spoke of that is flowne out of the Arke, and will never be drawne to your lure, never be disciplined. Set up Christs Kingdome, and it will bring in Arm-fulls of blessings to us and our posteritie, and make our Kingdome flourish. If men were but once acquainted with that royall Scepter and government, his sweet and easie yoake, they would quickly see the benefit of reformation, and what a heavy yoke the Prelacy hath been to our King and State and whole Land.</p>
               <p>Now having shewed the unlawfulnesse and evills of the offices, and tryed them both by the Word and by their fruits to be Antichristian. If any yet will be so ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turous against so cleare light to open their mouthes to plead for Episcopacy, &amp; oppose the setting up of Christs Kingly office in his throne and glory, we will shew them the danger of it for their warning, in two shorts Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="argument">
               <head>Argument IX.</head>
               <p>If the Prelates and their officers in the exercise of their unlawfull offices, doe many things in the worship of God without warrant of the Word of God, they are guilty of the sinne and punishment of <hi>Nadab,</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> of <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram.</hi> But so doe the Prelates and their Officers: as witnesse the whole source of their superstitions, and mens inventions of old, and late inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated abhominations of Jewish Popish and Heathenish fopperies and Ceremonies, which they have brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the worship of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo</hi> they are guilty of the like sinne and punishment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="argument">
               <head>Argument X.</head>
               <p>If <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu, Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> were so strangely punished for once presuming (in the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise of their lawfull offices) to doe that which they had
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:111535:20"/> no warrant for. What may the Prelates and all their confederates expect, but unheard of plagues, and strange punishments, for not once but many yeares, (after many warnings, and against light and knowledge abounding) doing many things in the worship of God without war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the word of God, and that in the exercise of their unlawfull offices. As those perished wonderfully in the withstanding <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and the word of God, shall not these Prelates and their partakers perish much more wonderfully in the withstanding of Christ, farre greater than <hi>Moses.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> were so strangely punished as fire from heaven consumed them, <hi>Levit.</hi> 10. 1. and the Earth opened her mouth and swallowed up quick, <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> and all their company, in the sight of <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and all the people; as we may see at large, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo</hi> the usurping Prelates and all their partakers, may look out for some strange unheard of punishment, from the Lord of Hoasts waiting for them and all that joyne with them in opposing Christ in his Kingly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and discipline. An end is come, the end is come, it watcheth for them, <hi>behold it is come,</hi> saith the Lord, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 7 6. It is recorded to all posteritie to the worlds end, as a brand of infamy upon all those that did partake in that opposition of <hi>Moses; They perished in the gainsaying of Core,</hi> Jude 11. Let all that plead for and partake in the unlawfull offices and practises of the Prelates, take heed to this in time: for the Lord is a strong God, who judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the whore and all her bratts and abhominations, <hi>Partake not in her sinnes, least yee partake in her plagues,</hi> Apoc. 18. 4. 8.</p>
               <q>Come out of the tents of these wicked men, <bibl>Numb. 16. 26.</bibl>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> Oh but (say some) we have had godly Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs,<note place="margin">The maine objection for Prelacy an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered.</note> and many learned men that have been Diocesan Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops as these are, and their government been long ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:111535:20"/> and Religion under it wonderfully flourished as in any Nation; And many worthy Instruments both in the Magistracy and Ministery, who have submitted to this government, which sure they would not have done if it were unlawfull and Antichristian.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> 1. The Church and faithfull Ministers have not all light at once or by one instrument, or yet by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny worthy lights, the remembrance of whom is preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and therefore as we would not detract any thing of their deservings from them, so must we not stick fast in their footsteps and goe no further. For still daily more and greater light of the Gospells brightnesse is to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected till the fulnesse of the Gentiles light come in, and be swallowed up in the Jewes fulnesse, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 12. Christ Jesus comes to his people as the Sunne arises, first, theres the dawning, then the darknesse expelled, and still brighter light, till the Sunne shine in his full strength.</p>
               <p>Secondly, These worthy Martyrs that were Dioce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>san Bishops, in the dawning of the Gospels light after a long darksome night of Popery, must be confessed to rise up in their Rochets out of the Papacy, and saw not presently into the unlawfulnesse of their office, yet some of them did and resigned, as <hi>Latimer;</hi> but they set themselves against the most cleare corruptions in doctrine and worship, so farre as they had light; as for Discipline it was so swept away in that great deluge of Popery, that no footsteps of it were to be seene in those times, or if any thing of it, yet but as the blinde man in the Gospell recovering his sight, saw men walking like trees, very darkly and confusedly.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, As their sight grew somewhat clearer, they saw into a godly discipline in the primitive Church, at which they aymed, as in the Preface to the Common prayer book at the Commination may be seene, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes they saw into another discipline than that they had amongst them, and brought with them out of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy, and is used to this day, therefore not the right dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:111535:21"/> and yet that primitive discipline, it is as proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble they saw at a great distance even then, and so left it to be searched out more clearly of the following genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and if they did see it any thing clearly, and if any thing hindered their light of breaking out into a more full reformation, we may thank even the Diocesan Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops for it, whose love of preheminence as ours now was the chiefe let in reformation in those times, as our Histories shew. So as we have little cause to boast of Bishops, as instruments of our reformation, if we were well acquainted with the state of those times, and what hinderers of Reformation the Bishops were, yea some of them that after suffered as Martyrs in Queene <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> time.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Some Bishops suffering as Martyrs after their morning light was clouded againe with hot perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions and stormes arising, even out of the same Seas they were in, by the changing of the winde in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> time, is no more an argument from their mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome that their office was good, than if a Cardinall in Rome or Spaine should professe the Gospell, and suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for it: his office were neverthelesse still Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christian.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, When these stormes were over, and a greater light broke out in Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, of a brigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Sunne-shine, multitudes of learned and godly Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters began to see clearly the foundation of Babell lay close and unseene in the office of Episcopacy, and in the keeping out Christs Kingly office especially, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore preached, writ, disputed, and suffered for it, even as Martyrs of those times by the tyranny of the Prelates who still oppose it to this day; as witnesse <hi>Cartwright, Parker, Fenner, Childerley, Chatterton, Traverse, Reinolds,</hi> and a many more; and at King <hi>James</hi> his first entrance about a thousand Ministers stood for Reformation of the Episcopall government, and for setting up of Christs Kingly office, who were in a few yeares wasted and spent and banished and devoured of these ravenous Wolves,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:111535:21"/> wives and children undone, and many families scattered, estates ruined for opposing this prelaticall office and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, so as little cause have we to boast of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, it hath been a bloody office to this day. Also many living yet can witnesse how a reformation hath been still petitioned for to Parliaments, even to this day: though with no successe, because their sins were not full, nor ours repented of and reformed.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, For many worthy instruments in Magistracy and Ministery, submitting to Episcopall government. <hi>Ans.</hi> 1. Divine examples, (but not humane) doe binde the Conscience, and make their practises rules to us; secondly, the Churches of a whole Nation, yea of many Nations, abounding with men of excellent parts, both in the Magistracy and Ministery, may yet long neglect some of Gods Ordinances, partly through ignorance, partly for want of assistance of the supreme Magistrate, as all the times of the Judges, and many good Kings, even from <hi>Joshua</hi> to the time of <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> the feast of keeping of boothes was neglected. Because, first, theres much naturall blindnesse in the best men: secondly, the Church often too carelesse in some weighty things: thirdly, men are ready to sit downe ere their work be half done, soone weary in so great and publick works as Reformation is: the spirit is willing, but the flesh is weake. Thus as they of old long neglected the feast of boothes, so have we too long neglected Christs discipline and government: the Lord pardon it.</p>
               <p>Seventhly and lastly, for the flourishing of Religion under the Prelates government, we have no cause to thanke them; they have alway persecuted the light and life of it, and done their best to put out the light, and to bring in an Egyptian darknesse againe: secondly, it hath been those they have most persecuted who have spread the greatest light, for a persecuted light is ever the brigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test, which shews it to be of God, and like to him, though darknesse comprehend it not; to him be glory that we have any light after so hot persecutions, and so many ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:111535:22"/> this is a signe our persecuted light shall prevaile: <hi>Tandem bona causa triumphat,</hi> was that renowned old Duke of Saxons Motto in all his bitter troubles with <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> Thirdly, though some see it not, so sleepy-headed in their ease and pleasures, they little regard the hazard Gods Ark is in, yet others that have watched long in the long winter night of the Churches troubles, for the daw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the day of deliverance, have found iil fruits of flourishing of Religion, and seene a great decay of the power of godlinesse these many yeares past, and many Ministers and professors fallen, some in following the sway of the times for worldly things, others through pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sillanimitie of spirit, into great decay of gifts and dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, all for want of Christs discipline, to keepe all men in their severall stations, and active in obedience; and to hedge in the Church from the inroades of enemies. The Lord teach us the use and benefit of, and open our eyes to see the want of, &amp; pardon our so long neglect of Christs Kingly office.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>Conclusion of all.</head>
               <p>Since now the pretended divine Authoritie of the Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchy is fayled in the foundation, and left them no foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, but in the filthy dunghill of the Canon Law of the Popes Authoritie, exalted above the Scriptures, in which they Mother like have built their nests, as in the clefts of the rocks of the seven hilled Citie. And they in Gods just judgement so blinded and of late confounded in their Councells, as to cast off his Majesties royall Authoritie, by which they have stood too long: and not a little tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched upon, they deserve to finde and feele, that <hi>He beares not the sword in vaine,</hi> Rom. 13. 4. but is Gods <hi>vindex</hi> of his own and subjects wrongs many wayes, so especially in opposing Christ so long in his Kingly office, and now at last in all his offices. As they by the abuse of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties sword have ruined many, so by the same sword let them perish; <hi>Who so sheddeth mens blood, by man shall his
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:111535:22"/> blood be shed; He that killeth with the sword, shall be killed with the sword,</hi> Gen. 9. 6. Apoc. 13. 10. Matth. 26. 52. the mouth of the Lord hath spoken it, and we waite the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of it. The Lord put into the hearts of our royall King, and of this honourable Parliament, to fulfill his will upon Babell and all her bratts and abhominations, <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>Jerem. 50. 24. 26.</bibl>
                  <q>I have laid a snare for thee, and thou art also taken O Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, and wast not aware, thou art found and also caught, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause thou hast striven against the Lord. Tread her in heapes, destroy her utterly, let nothing of her be left.</q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
               <head>The benefits of Reformation of Discipline.</head>
               <p>Then shall Christs workmen with great alacritie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to build the house of God, which these men have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced and defiled, and make a beautifull habitation for the Lord Jesus to dwell and delight in, and great shall be his glory in the midst of us, in presence and protection. Then shall our eyes see our King in his glory on his throne, and our Jerusalem in peace, <hi>Isa.</hi> 33. 17. 20.</p>
               <p>Then also shall King <hi>Charles</hi> his throne be more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious than any his predecessors; then shall Judgement and Justice flow forth as a mighty River, to sweep away all sinne and wickednesse.</p>
               <p>Then shall our King be to the Just as raine upon the<note place="margin">Psal. 72.</note> grasse new mowen; the Mountaines shall bring forth peace, and the little hills righteousnesse; Court and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey shall flourish, the Land shall bring forth her en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease, and God even our God shall blesse us, and all the ends of the Earth shall feare him, <hi>Psal.</hi> 67. 6. When they heare and see what great things he will doe for us.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:111535:23"/>
               <head>A short appendix touching Discipline.</head>
               <p>Since in this great and honourable High Court of Parliament, every subject is so concerned as bound to submit to what shall be therein established, therefore as a member and well-wisher of the well-fare of the whole body, I crave leave for a word or two concerning disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline. Since tis now in every mans mouth, what forme of discipline we shall have, when the Prelaticall, as none of Christs, shall be justly abolished. Which seems to me to upbraid the ignorance and unthankfulnesse of this age, (the fruits of Episcopacy) as if men in the Sun-shine should complaine of darknesse: or as if the Spirit of Christ which descended upon the Apostles, teaching all things, and leading them into all truth, should have left them wandring at randome without direction in governing the house of God; or yet left it arbitrary to mens seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall minds, humours, and frames. The Scriptures are full and plentifully furnished with instructions for the whole frame and fashions of the house of GOD, which all brought together and set up, would be a beautifull stru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture; it is the tabernacle of God with men, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. walking in the midst of them, <hi>Apoc. 2. 1. Luk.</hi> 20. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6. 16.</note> It were a piece of heavens happinesse to see it advanced in the same form Christ hath appointed and his Apostles practised and instituted in all the Churches, to be perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall to the worlds end. All I have to say in one word, tis that I would consent to; keepe close to that patterne, and beware of the severall frames of mens braines, to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne the Church by humane policy, after the manner of earthly Kingdomes and States, which was the first thing brought in the plague of Episcopacy, and will still leave a back-dore to papall tyranny in the Church of God: from which we can never be secured untill Christs own government be established, tis his own Scepter must rule and no inventions of men or Angels, if possibly they could be consulted with.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>